International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) Records
International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) Records
1954-1991
International Congress of University Adult Education
3.5 linear ft.
The International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) was formed in 1960 to exchange information and opinions about activities in adult education, and to discuss ways of advancing adult education on a broad front. Records include correspondence, membership records, memoranda, minutes and reports. Organizations represented in the collection include the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults and Unesco. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include Alexander N. Charters, Alexander Albert Liveright, and Paul Henry Sheats.
149075
Biographical History
The International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) was formed in 1960, immediately following the Unesco World Conference on Adult Education in Montreal, Canada. Thirty-five adult educators from 14 countries met at the Sagamore Conference Center of Syracuse University to exchange information and opinions about their activities in adult education, and to discuss ways of advancing adult education on a broad front. The Congress acts as an agency of communication and liaison, and a clearinghouse of information and ideas at the international level. The Congress received support in its early years from the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults which provided Alexander Albert Liveright as secretariat. The Congress has sponsored world and regional international meetings of university adult educators, promoted the study of comparative adult education, and published a journal and occasional papers.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) Records include correspondence, membership records, memoranda, minutes and reports. Organizations represented in the collection include the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults and Unesco.
Correspondence covers 1959-1968. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include Alexander N. Charters, Alexander Albert Liveright, and Paul Henry Sheats.Membership records includes both individual and institutional memberships from 1963-1967. Reports and memoranda includes ICUAE, UNESCO and miscellaneous reports. General information such as a directory of colleges involved in adult education and ICUAE's constitution, bylaws and editorial policies resides in General files. Committee files includes the Executive Committee, the Program Planning Committee and the Inter-University International Summer School Committee. Meetings comprises minutes from meetings in various locations (most are in Syracuse). Publications contains several issues of ICUAE's quarterly journal, dating from 1964-1974.
Material which could not be usefully placed in other categories is collected at the end in Miscellanea.
Arrangement of the Collection
The series themselves are not in any particular order. Within each series, most material is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
The following are particularly closely related to the ICUAE Records:
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander A. Liveright Papers
Paul Sheats Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Charters, Alexander N.; Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-1984.; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; International Congress of University Adult Education -- Archives.; Unesco.; Internation Congress of University Adult Education Journal.; Adult education.; International education.; Correspondence.; Journals (periodicals); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority of collection, transfer from ERIC and/or University Archives, 1968-1970.
ICUAE journal issues, gift of Alexander Charters, 2011.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1959-1964 (May), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Jun)-1968, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)
- Membership records
  - Individual memberships, 1963-1965; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Individual memberships, 1965-1967; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Institutional memberships, 1963-1965; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Institutional memberships, 1965-1967; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Membership rosters, 1961-1966 (Box 4)
- Reports and memoranda
  - International Congress of University Adult Education, 1960-1965 (Box 4)
  - UNESCO
    - 1954-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963-1967, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-1967 (Box 5)
    See also Miscellaneous: Discussion group report, "The Concept of Continuing Education"
- General files
  - Directory, "Universities and Colleges Engaged in Adult Education", 1962 (Box 7)
  - Incorporation, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1963 (Box 7)
    See also Miscellanea: Constitution and history
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Editorial policy, undated (Box 7)
- Committee files
  - Executive Committee
    - 1961, Jamaica (Box 7)
    - 1961, Syracuse [NY] (Box 7)
    - 1962, Ghana (Box 7)
    - 1962, Stratford, Ontario (Box 7)
    - 1963, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1964, Sydney (Box 7)
    - 1964, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1965, Krogerup, Denmark (Box 7)
    - 1966, Boston (Box 7)
    - 1966, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1966, Buffalo (Box 7)
    - 1967, New York (Box 7)
    - 1968, Leeds, England (Box 7)
    - 1970, Montreal (Box 7)
  - Program Planning Committee, Hamilton, Ontario, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Inter-University International Summer School Committee, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 7)
- Meetings
  - Sagamore Conference, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Unesco staff meeting, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Meetings of officers
    - 1962, Chicago (Box 7)
    - 1963, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1963, New York (Box 7)
    - 1963, Boston (Box 7)
    - 1964, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1965, New York (Box 7)
    - 1967, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1968, Toronto (Box 7)
    - 1968, Syracuse (Box 7)
    - 1969, Syracuse (Box 7)
  - Annual Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Meeting, 1966 (Box 7)
- Publications
  - International Congress of Adult Education Journal, 1964-1974; 1979; 1991; quarterly journal of the organization; 18 issues (Box 8)
    1964: March (Volume III, No. 2)
    1965: March, May (Volume IV, No.s 1 and 2)
    1965: January (Volume V, No. 1)
    1966: December (Volume V, No. 2)
    1967: June (Volume VI, No. 1)
    1968: April, September, December (Volume VII, No.s 1, 2, 3)
    1969: December (Volume VIII, No. 1)
    1970: July, September (Volume IX, No.s 2 and 3)
    1971: April, July, November (Volume X, No.s 1, 2, 3)
    1974: April (Volume XIII, No. 1)
    1979: April (Volume XVIII, No. 1)
    1991: November (Volume XXX, No. 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Constitution and history, 1962 (Box 6)
    See also General files: Constitutution and bylaws
  - Discussion group report, "The Concept of Continuing Education", undated (Box 6)
  - First World Conference, position papers, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Institut de la Promotion Supérieure du Travail, Toulouse, France, 1965 (Box 6)
  - N.E.A. Convention, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Speeches
    - Labuda, Gerard, undated (Box 6)
    - Lengrand, P., 1965 (Box 6)
    - Schwartz, B., 1964 (Box 6)
  - University College, Dar es Salaam, 1966 (Box 6)